our next micronutrient is
magnesium oh my goodness could I go on
and on and on about the physiological
benefits of magnesium it is involved in
well over 600 reactions in your body
from cell signaling vascular function
ATP production protein synthesis uh
neuroplasticity learning memory and I
could basically think of anything that
happens in your body and magnesium
Central to that I don't have to draw
this out then it's pretty easy for you
to assume as is going to be a important
role in your brain pre and post injury
we also have very strong data if you are
deficient in magnesium you have
associations with a host of
comorbidities health conditions type two
diabetes metabolic syndrome hypertension
headaches is another common one
migraines heart disease so on and so
forth we know that it probably inhibits
receptors that are directly targets of
anti-depressants as well and as a strong
contributor to that brain excitotoxicity
after injury so you do not want to be
deficient in magnesium you can listen to
read almost anything in the sports
performance realm and you will see
magnesium as a top tier supplementation
it is really robust and a a strong line
of evidence and and recommended by again
many people in this field but
surprisingly the S soe only three here
there's a well documented drop in
magnesium especially near Central
neurons after TBI and the extent of that
drop is associated with the severity of
the injury and the level of Behavioral
disturbances so not only the injury but
your symptoms as well animal and human
research here from the animals It's
associated with edema brain and blood
concentrations calcium problems like we
talked about earlier um these are going
to result in those behavioral
modifications memory cognitive function
spatial and working memory and so on and
so forth from the actual human stuff
couple of studies that are worth drawing
attention to here one looked at acute
tbis in kids and saw a significant
reduction in postconcussion severity
scores 48 hours after the injury when
they used 400 mg of magnesium twice per
day now another study was used a similar
design and didn't find a benefit but
this was actually using magnesium from
an IV for 5 days now no really actually
knows why this one trial worked the
other one didn't the obvious thought is
maybe there's something that happens
when you adjust it through your stomach
that aids in digestion or makes it more
bioavailable but when you took with the
IV it didn't to me that's honestly not a
great answer but I don't have any other
reason to think that that happened so
really honestly to summarize here it is
very very safe it's very little harm it
has so many other health and performance
related benefits there's so many Health
consequences that are associated with
magnesium
deficiency it helps with symptoms and
behaviors that are Hallmarks of TBI like
we've talked
about so I know the soe is technically
three but personally it's it's about as
high in the list as I could think one
supplement could be the dosages we
described one more time 400 milligrams
per day the timing doesn't matter you'll
want to have some in their pre as well
as post injury and you could take it at
any point in the day now depending on
the type or form that you use you might
want to take it later in the evening
some people report and depending on the
type magnesium helps you fall asleep I
personally feel no effect at all but
most people do I still then take my
magnesium at night just because just in
case there is all kinds of forms you've
heard of magnesium 38 at this point
bisglycinate malate and right now I
don't know of any compelling evidence to
suggest one of those forms is any better
than another obviously magnesium 38 has
become more popular recently and that
may turn out to be more effective it may
not I'm not sure there's just not enough
data for us to have a really an answer
at this point and so you can take
whatever form sits best with you the
obvious risks associated with magnesium
are the GI distress bisglycinate malate
3 and8 are generally pretty well handled
and so you you shouldn't have too many
issues with it if you want to get it
strictly from food you're looking now at
things like pumpkin seeds chia seeds
almonds and spinach uh typically I think
pumpkin seeds are about the highest
you'll find they've got around 200
milligrams of magnesium per 100 grams
roasted again you can do some math there
and realize all right that's at least
200 grams of roasted pumpkin seeds I'd
have to get to get to my you know 400
milligrams which is honestly quite a lot
not impossible some people eat tons of
almonds and spinach and things like that
especially vegetarians and vegans but it
is quite a bit given how cheap effective
and easy to handle and how many other
things are benefited with magnesium as a
supplement n we use it pretty commonly
if you enjoyed this clip you can watch
the full episode by clicking here